Long time no see, Flamme.
真是好久不見了，弗蘭梅
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
Bargland.
操控大地的魔法
Young ones are just too hot-blooded.
年輕人真是血氣方剛
I couldn't care less about the privilege.
我才不在乎什麼特權
Hey, why do you feel that way?
我說啊，你為什麼這樣覺得？
Do you even need to ask?
這種事還需要問嗎？
When it comes to magic,
魔法這種東西
the process of searching for it is the most fun part.
追尋它的過程才是最有趣的時候
That is all.
僅此而已
I see.
這樣啊
Time flies, doesn't it?
時間過得還真快，不是嗎？
The apprentice whom I raised on a whim
我一時興起培養的徒弟
has already brought over her own apprentice.
都已經帶著她的徒弟來了
This is Frieren.
她叫芙莉蓮
An elf, huh?
精靈嗎？
You're strong. I like you.
很強嘛，很合我意
Name whatever spell you desire. I will bestow one upon you.
想要什麼魔法儘管說 我可以傳授你一個魔法
A spell I desire?
想要的魔法？
I know almost all the spells found in
史上所有魔導書所記載的魔法知識
every grimoire written in history.
我幾乎都知道
Mages spend
所謂的魔法使
their whole lives
總會窮盡畢生之力
in search of the spell of their dreams.
尋求夢想中的魔法
Tell me yours. I will bestow it upon you.
說吧，我會教給你
I don't want it.
不用了
The process of searching for magic is the most fun part.
魔法這種東西 追尋它的過程才是最有趣的時候
Flamme,
弗蘭梅
this girl is no good, after all.
這孩子果然不行
She lacks ambition… fiery ambition.
缺乏野心…那種炙熱的野心
Master,
師父
she will defeat the Demon King one day.
有朝一日這孩子會打敗魔王
I believe mages like her
我相信像她這樣的魔法使
will be the pioneers of an era of peace.
能開創和平的時代
Are you saying that I can't?
你是說我的話就不行嗎？
Someone who pursues fighting, like you, cannot kill the Demon King.
像你這樣追求戰鬥的人 是不會殺掉魔王的
It's not possible for people like us.
我們這種人是做不到的
Think about it, Master.
師父，畢竟呢
I bet you can't imagine yourself living in an era of peace.
相信你也想像不出 活在和平時代的自己吧
Frieren is a mage who was meant for an era of peace.
芙莉蓮是和平時代的魔法使啊
Very good.
很好
This is how mages ought to be.
魔法使就應該是這樣
Damn it. I can't freeze him at all.
可惡，根本凍不住這傢伙
Our difference in mana is too great.
我們的魔力相差太大了
Nephtear.
釋放冰箭的魔法
-Kanne, defend us! -I know!
-康涅，快防禦！ -我知道！
You two ran around, making quite the show,
你們一直到處亂跑，太招搖了
so I know your abilities to some extent.
所以我大概知道你們有多少能耐
Your ice magic lacks lethality
你的冰魔法缺乏殺傷力
and you're a mage who can't fight unless there's water.
而你是只要沒有水 就無法戰鬥的魔法使
What did I get myself into?
看看我都給自己找了什麼事情
This really is nothing but babysitting.
還真的就是哄哄小孩
Well, that's harsh.
聽起來還真刺耳
Look at you and your flashy magic.
看看你自己吧，用了那麼浮誇的魔法
Are you sure your mana is going to last?
你才該確定自己魔力撐不撐得住吧
You two are from the Magic Academy, right?
你們都出身自魔法學校吧？
Are those old people still teaching
那些老人難道還在教
attrition warfare that relies mainly on defensive magic?
以防禦魔法為主的消耗戰嗎？
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Let me give you a lesson on the history of magic.
我來幫你們上點魔法史吧
Defensive magic, which was developed to counter Zoltraak,
為反擊殺人魔法開發出來的防禦魔法
has a strong resistance against magic itself,
對魔法本身的抵禦力很強
but its capability to defend physical attacks
但是抵擋物理攻擊的能力
has hardly made any improvements.
可謂沒有絲毫的進步
Of course, there is a reason behind this.
當然這是有原因的
That's because it was already enough to block
因為這種魔法就已經足夠抵擋
physical attacks of monsters and warriors.
魔物跟戰士的物理攻擊了
Defensive magic must not be overengineered.
防禦魔法絕不能過度設計
Trying to make it perfect will overcomplicate the procedure
過度要求完美 只會讓魔法術式太過複雜
and have a critical effect on the activation speed.
對於發動速度會產生致命影響
The history of magic is all about offense and defense.
魔法史不外乎就是攻防的歷史
So now, most modern offensive magic
因此更現代的攻擊魔法
are spells that manipulate physical matter.
就是以操縱物質為主
Can you tell what I'm trying to say?
明白我的意思了嗎？
No Kanne, dodge!
不行，康涅，快躲開！
My magic allows me to
我的魔法
attack using the overwhelming mass of physical matter.
是用壓倒性的大量物質進行攻擊
Just go to sleep.
就這樣睡吧
Oh, come on.
拜託了
I don't enjoy bullying people.
我可不喜歡折磨別人
Or do you actually want me to kill you?
還是說，你真的要我殺了你？
Isn't it careless of you to get that close?
這麼靠近不會太無所顧忌了嗎？
You know, 60% of the human body is water.
人的體內可是有六成都是水
So what?
那又如何？
Magic is all about visualizing.
所謂的魔法即是想像的世界
Are you able to visualize how water is distributed in the body?
難道你能想像 水在人的體內是如何分布的嗎？
Can you visualize extracting and manipulating it?
你能想像 把水分抽出並操縱的畫面嗎？
How would you even do that against a mage who is
面對受到大量魔力保護的魔法使
protected by a ton of mana?
難道還可以做到這點嗎？
If you can't visualize it, you can't realize it with magic.
如果想像不出來，就無法用魔法實現
And plus, even if there was water here,
再者，就算這裡有水好了
a little girl like her is no threat to me.
這樣的小丫頭 對我根本不足以構成威脅
You won't even fall for our bluff? What a mean adult.
我們虛張聲勢都不上當嗎？ 真是討厭的大人
But there's one thing I found out.
不過我發現了一件事
You're lying, aren't you, you bastard?
你說謊了吧，你這個混蛋？
If you love fighting enough to lecture us on it,
你這麼喜歡戰鬥，不惜對我們說教
you would've defeated us somewhere where there was water.
那麼就應該會在有水的地方打倒我們
What are you afraid of?
你在怕什麼？
Don't do anything.
給我安份一點
My job is to put you two to sleep.
我只負責讓你們倆睡一會
Unless Denken loses, that is.
前提是鄧肯沒有輸的情況
At this rate, it's going to end with me running out of mana.
再這樣下去，我的魔力遲早會耗盡
This is a bit tough for an old man like me.
這樣對待我這個老人稍嫌苛刻了吧
Sorry, but I'll have to end this quickly,
抱歉了，我得盡快結束這場戰鬥
Frieren.
芙莉蓮
Waldgose.
颳起龍捲風的魔法
Daosdorg.
將風化為業火的魔法
That old fart… What kind of battle is this?
那個老糊塗…這是哪門子的戰鬥？
That old man is going all out, isn't he?
那個爺爺真是竭盡全力呢
Will the barrier be okay?
結界撐得住嗎？
Don't be silly.
別蠢了
This barrier was put up by the Great Mage Serie.
這可是大魔法使賽莉耶設下的結界
It's not something you can break by using force.
並不是靠蠻力就能擊破的東西
I see. I'll take your word for it.
這樣啊，那就好
By the way, someone has been
話說回來，從昨晚開始
deciphering the barrier from around last night.
就有人在解析結界
What for?
有何居心？
I don't know.
不知道
Either way, it's useless.
不管怎麼做都是沒用的
As if there is a mage who can surpass Serie in this world.
這個世界不會有 能超越賽莉耶的魔法使
Catastravia.
釋放裁決之光的魔法
No way! A counterattack?
不可能，居然反擊了？
I barraged her with arrows of light.
明明用光之箭連續攻擊她了
There was no time to--
根本不該有空檔…
I'm out of mana… So this is the end, huh?
沒有魔力了…到此為止了嗎？
Unbelievable…
真是難以置信
Until the very end, she used nothing but basic combat magic.
這傢伙直到最後 都只有用基礎戰鬥魔法
This was no different
這樣根本就是
than a practice match against an apprentice mage.
對見習魔法使的指導戰鬥
I'm shocked.
真是令人震驚
I've come this far, and yet there is still someone better than me.
我都已經身居高位 卻沒想到居然人外有人
Tell me where Laufen is.
告訴我拉歐芬的位置
I'm sure you know. I'll be taking back our Stille.
你的話應該會知道 我要拿回我們的隕鐵鳥
If you were in my shoes, would you say the location?
易地而處的話，你會說出位置嗎？
That's true…
說得也是
Laufen, I know you're hiding nearby.
拉歐芬，我知道你躲在附近
Bring the Stille to me.
把隕鐵鳥還給我
If you don't come, I will kill Denken.
你不來，我就殺了鄧肯
Don't do it, Laufen. She has no intent to kill.
別照做，拉歐芬，她沒有動殺心
I'm sure you can tell.
你是知道的吧
The old man was defeated? Compared to me…
爺爺被打敗了？她跟我相比的話…
No, even compared to Richter, she is a far superior mage.
不，就是跟利希塔相比 她也是遠遠更加高等的魔法使
But she has her guard down. She isn't touching the old man.
但是她大意了，她沒碰到爺爺
Don't use Jilwer.
不要用高速移動的魔法
Stay hidden.
好好躲著
She can detect even the slightest amount of mana.
哪怕只有丁點魔力，她都能感知到
At this distance, I can retrieve the old man and escape!
這個距離可以救出爺爺然後逃走！
Don't do it. It's a trap.
不要行動，這是陷阱
I guess I have no choice.
看來是沒其他辦法了
I'd rather not do things like this, though.
雖然我並不喜歡做這種事情
I found you.
找到了
You fool.
笨蛋
You're so immature.
真是不成熟
It was obvious that she had no intent to kill.
你明明也知道她沒有動殺心
But she was
但是那傢伙
ready to hurt you until you were barely alive.
準備把爺爺你打到奄奄一息喔
But we still would have won.
就算是這樣，也是吾等獲勝了
Old man, why would you go that far to become a first-class mage?
爺爺，為什麼你要為了 成為一級魔法使不惜做到這個地步？
You already have everything,
財富、權勢或其他的東西
from wealth to power, don't you?
你不是什麼都不缺了嗎？
My hometown is deep inside of the Northern Plateau.
老夫的故鄉在北部高原的深處
Because the demons have made a ruckus,
都是因為魔族作亂的緣故
only first-class mages can get in now.
現在只有一級魔法使可以通行
I hadn't visited the cemetery in a while, so I wanted to go.
我只是很久沒有去掃墓了
That is all.
僅此而已
Shouldn't you go help those kids?
你不快去救那些小鬼嗎？
Although, it may be too late.
雖然可能已經太晚了
Richter will kill them
利希塔會在跟你交手前
before fighting you.
殺掉她們
He's the kind of man who can make rational decisions like that.
他是能做出這種合理判斷的男人
There's no need to worry about that. Those two will win.
那樣的話就不用擔心了，她們贏定了
I've just finished deciphering the barrier.
結界的解析剛剛結束
Who would've thought that Denken would lose.
沒想到鄧肯竟然會打輸
Well then…
那麼…
Babysitting time is over now.
哄小孩的時間結束了
He's seriously trying to kill us.
他真的要殺掉我們
We won't even last a minute.
我們連一分鐘都撐不住
The barrier? Deciphering?
結界？解析？
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Frieren, don't tell me…
芙莉蓮，難道你…
Genau…
葛納烏…
Don't worry.
不用擔心
It's impossible even if the world turned upside down.
就算天地顛倒過來 也不可能會發生那種事
It's going to break.
結界要破了
Sense, who is that elf mage?
冉則，那位精靈魔法使是何方神聖？
According to the examinee roster, her name is Frieren.
根據考生名冊，她名叫芙莉蓮
That's the same name as the mage from the party of heroes.
跟勇者一行人當中的魔法使同名
And apparently, she had the Holy Emblem.
據說她還擁有聖杖證明
The last great mage, huh?
最後的大魔法使嗎？
You've really done it, Frieren.
真有兩下子呢，芙莉蓮
What a way to greet someone for the first time in a thousand years.
睽違千年不見，還真是不得了的問候
This is why I don't get tired of being a mage.
正因如此，當個魔法使 從不會讓我感到厭倦呢
In the world of magic, the world can turn upside down.
在魔法世界裡，天地是能顛倒過來的
I can't believe you actually broke the barrier.
真不敢相信你真的打破了結界
Why did you do that?
你為什麼要這麼做？
Because I felt bad for Kanne.
因為我替康涅感到可惜
Magic shouldn't have limitations.
魔法應該是自由的
The mage who can manipulate water, huh?
能操控水流的魔法使嗎？
Magic is all about visualizing.
所謂的魔法即是想像的世界
Can you imagine winning against a mage who can manipulate water, in the rain?
你能想像在雨中 打贏操控水流的魔法使嗎？
I can't, at least.
至少我是想像不出來
I'm sure Richter is the same.
利希塔那傢伙應該也是
The barrier…
結界…
-What just happened? -The rain…
-發生什麼事了？ -雨水…
Whatever, I can assess the situation later.
不管了，待會再確認情況
I have to finish them off quickly--
必須盡快幹掉她們…
You finally let your guard down.
總算是抓到你的破綻了
Your mana is unstable because you're rushing.
你的魔力因為焦急都變得不穩定了
This level of stalling is nothing!
這種程度的拖延時間不算什麼！
Now I understand
現在我懂了
why you were scared of her water-manipulating magic.
為什麼你會怕她的水流操控魔法了
Just like you said,
正如你所說的
this is an attack using the overwhelming mass of physical matter.
這就是你所謂的 壓倒性的大量物質攻擊
Lawine,
拉比涅
don't let him escape.
別讓他逃了
Reamstroha.
操控水的魔法
There is nowhere to escape anyway.
反正也無處可逃啊
This is why I hate water.
所以我才討厭水
You won, huh?
看來是打贏了
Let's get out of here quickly.
我們趕快離開這裡吧
We have two hours until sundown, but can you conceal your mana until then?
雖然離日落還有兩小時 但你們能抑制魔力到那時候嗎？
We don't even have any mana left to conceal.
魔力都耗盡了 哪裡還用得著抑制啊？
I see. Good job.
這樣啊，做得很好
Don't pat me.
別摸頭
Sorry.
抱歉
It couldn't be helped.
那也是沒辦法的事
Both Denken and I are all out of mana.
鄧肯跟我都已經耗盡魔力了
There's only two hours left. We're done for.
只剩下兩小時，已經無力可回天了
Laufen, can you break this restraint?
拉歐芬，你能解開這個束縛嗎？
Are you kidding? The amount of mana in this restraint is crazy.
你在開玩笑嗎？ 這個束縛的魔力可不是普通的強
Then how about the tree? Cut it down.
那從樹這邊下手呢？把樹砍倒吧
Denken, it's not possible anymore.
鄧肯，已經不可能了
I don't have enough mana to use Jilwer anymore either.
我也沒有足以使出 高速移動魔法的魔力了
Richter, Laufen,
利希塔、拉歐芬
what do you think an Imperial Mage would do in this situation?
你們以為宮廷魔法使這時候會怎樣？
They'd persist until the end, no matter how unsightly it is.
不管多難看都要堅持到最後
Let's search for traces of battles fought by other parties and follow them.
去搜尋其他小隊戰鬥後的痕跡吧
You know, Fern,
話說，費倫
you are so boring.
你真的好無聊喔
You seriously only use basic magic.
你真的只用基礎魔法耶
Please bring that up to Mistress Frieren.
那種話請跟芙莉蓮大人說
Oh right, that elf was your master, wasn't she?
說起來，那個精靈就是你師父吧？
It's her fault that we've become drenched,
她害我們淋成落湯雞了
so you'd better scold her.
一定要好好說說她喔
I already plan to.
我正有此意
Also, I am free to use any spell as long as it's not combat related.
但我可以自由使用與戰鬥無關的魔法
Now that you mention it, you did use a spell to capture the bird.
聽你這麼說 你確實是用了抓鳥的魔法
What other spells can you use?
你還會用哪些魔法？
Let's see… A spell that lets you see through clothes.
我想想…讓衣服看起來變透明的魔法
I'm not going to use it.
我不會用的
Hey, I'm sorry to interrupt your fun little conversation,
話說，雖說不該在 你們聊得正開心時打斷你們
but I wouldn't reveal all my tricks if I were you.
但是不要亮出自己的底牌比較好吧
From the second stage of the exam, we will become enemies.
下一階段的考試開始時 我們就是敵人了
That's true.
說得也是
Sorry.
對不起囉
But you still could've warmed up to us a little more, Four-eyes.
不過，眼鏡男 你要是可以對我們再更親切點就好了
There they are. A defeated party.
找到了，戰敗的小隊
I saw the dead body of their party member nearby.
我在附近看到他們死去隊員的屍體
There is no chance for them to pass the exam,
已經不可能通過考試了
but they're still holding onto that precious Stille.
但他們依舊死死抱著隕鐵鳥
Are you going to negotiate with them?
你要去交涉看看嗎？
They wouldn't agree to it.
他們不會答應的
If I were in their shoes,
換作是我的話
I would refuse even if they paid me.
就是付我錢，我都不會答應
Why?
為什麼？
Because it's irritating.
因為這樣很讓人生氣啊
It's an emotional issue.
純粹是感性使然
Laufen, you wait here.
拉歐芬，你在這裡等
Steal the Stille when you see the chance. Richter, follow me.
找到機會就偷走隕鐵鳥 利希塔，跟我來
What are you planning to do?
你打算怎麼做？
You're going head-on?
要正面進攻？
We don't have any mana left.
我們已經耗盡魔力了
Can't you tell?
你看不出來嗎？
The same applies to them as well.
他們也是一樣的情形
Face up to it.
做好覺悟
You're a man, aren't you?
你是個男人吧？
Hey, you're kidding, right?
喂，你是開玩笑的吧？
It's time for a fistfight!
肉搏戰登場！
It's time.
時間到了
At this time, we will end the first stage of the exam.
現在宣布第一階段考試結束
A total of 18 people in 6 parties have passed the first stage.
第一階段考試共有6隊18人通過
The second stage will be in three days.
三天後進行第二階段考試
We will share the details later.
後續會再通知各位考試內容
That is all.
以上
You're dismissed.
解散
It's already been two days since they went to take the exam.
她們去參加考試已經過了兩天
Fern isn't here to get mad at me even if I stay up late.
就算起床起得晚了，費倫也不會罵我
I'm so happy, it's almost scary.
幸福到都覺得有點恐怖了
Sounds like you have it pretty tough.
聽起來真辛苦，小哥
It's not yours.
不是你的
-No worries, Mistress Frieren. -Don't talk about that.
-放心吧，芙莉蓮大人 -別再談這個話題了
-You're more spoiled than me. -It's not even your birthday.
-你比我還要受到寵愛呢 -明明不是生日
-You have to eat vegetables too. -and you get such treatment?
-青菜也要吃 -這樣太奢侈了吧？
-This person is annoying. -We're not a party anymore.
-這個人好麻煩 -我們已經不是隊友了
"Future Enemies."
《下次開始就是敵人》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻